const e="civiledu",t=200,a=48,o=[{id:389,question:"Which of the following statements may be true about the behaviour of the candidates in the diagram?",option:{a:"The candidates are doing what is ethical",b:"Candidates involved in malpractice should be banned for life",c:"Their action can also affect innocent candidates",d:"Their misconduct will guarantee a reliable certificate"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:390,question:"Based on the above diagram, the candidates would not have cheated if",option:{a:"they were well-spaced",b:"there was an invigilator",c:"they were hardworking",d:"there was nobody to copy from"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:391,question:"In which year did the United Nations General Assembly adopt the Universal Declaration of Human Rights?",option:{a:"1945",b:"1946",c:"1947",d:"1948"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:392,question:"Two forms of road signs are regulatory and",option:{a:"punitive",b:"informative",c:"persuasive",d:"inhibitive"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:393,question:"Which of the following factors does not affect interpersonal relationship?",option:{a:"Communication",b:"Withdrawal",c:"Compatibility",d:"Forgiveness"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:394,question:"The following cadre of students are the main target for campus cult membership except",option:{a:"students from wealthy homes",b:"students from influential parents",c:"bold and morally sound students",d:"wayward and fun-loving students"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:395,question:"The National Agency for Food and Drug Administration and Control (NAFDAC) was established in",option:{a:"1993",b:"1996",c:"1999",d:"2001"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:396,question:"National Agency for the Prohibition of Traffic in Persons (NAPTIP) is an initiative of",option:{a:"Federal Government of Nigeria",b:"United States Agency for International Development",c:"Woman Trafficking and Child Labour Eradication 	Foundation",d:"United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:397,question:"World AIDS day is observed on",option:{a:"20th May",b:"30th July",c:"27th August",d:"1th December"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:398,question:"An enabling environment created to help an individual have effective control of his/her situation is known as",option:{a:"reinforcement",b:"empowerment",c:"endowment",d:"enhancement"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:399,question:"In order to avoid undue interference in the process of governance, there should be",option:{a:"clear cut separation of governmental powers",b:"proper fusion of governmental powers and functions",c:"more roles for traditional rulers in the governmental process",d:"additional responsibility for local government council"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:400,question:"Red-tapism is one the shortcomings of",option:{a:"private enterprise",b:"public service",c:"non-governmental organization",d:"pressure groups"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:401,question:"An ideology that aims at promoting national consciousness and identity is",option:{a:"nationalism",b:"socialization",c:"civic culture",d:"progressivism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:402,question:"Human rights are described as inviolable mainly because they are",option:{a:"authoritative declaration",b:"enforceable everywhere",c:"not to be unnecessarily taken away",d:"legal declaration instruments"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:403,question:"Law and order can best be maintained in Nigeria through the",option:{a:"prohibition of public protest",b:"enforcement of rules and regulations",c:"use of divide and rule policy",d:"promotion of indigenization policy"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:404,question:"A responsible parent is someone who",option:{a:"cares and provides for the children",b:"indulges the children because of love",c:"works in order to receive salary",d:"employs house-helps to take care of the children"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:405,question:"A major way of promoting responsible parenthood is through",option:{a:"sex education",b:"sound education",c:"population control measures",d:"tax reduction measures"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:406,question:"Which of the following is not included in the stages of interpersonal relationship?",option:{a:"Rejuvenation",b:"Deterioration",c:"Termination",d:"Continuation"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:407,question:"Cultism in tertiary institutions in Nigeria was originally introduced to",option:{a:"perpetuate the use of local gin and alcohol",b:"harass opponents of university administrators",c:"fight colonialism and oppressive rules",d:"promote inter-communal marriages."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:408,question:"Which of the following is not a function of the National Drug Law Enforcement Agency (NDLEA)?",option:{a:"Applying and implementing all drug laws",b:"Arresting, investigating and prosecuting drug traffickers",c:"Undertaking the registration of companies dealing 	in drugs",d:"Carrying out enlightenment campaigns on drug trafficking"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:409,question:"An individual who finds it difficult to control in-take of drug is known as drug",option:{a:"baron",b:"traffickers",c:"mogul",d:"addict"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:410,question:"The NDLEA personnel are not usually found in",option:{a:"international airports",b:"seaports",c:"border crossings",d:"foreign embassies"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:411,question:"Which of the following statements best describes Human Trafficking?",option:{a:"Recruitment of youths as casual workers",b:"Desperate desire by youths to travel abroad",c:"Buying and selling of humans for selfish purposes",d:"Transportation of gods and service through human portage"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:412,question:"From the above write-up what category of Kantoguan youth deserves to be effectively empowered?",option:{a:"Children of the ruling political class",b:"Unemployed youths and school drop-outs",c:"University undergraduates",d:"Youth wing of religious organizations"},section:"One major trend in Kantoga Republic today, especially during elections, is the engagement of youths by some politicians for political thuggery, rigging, stuffing of ballot boxes and other related electoral offences. Most of the youths who are engaged in these crimes have no means of livelihood or are school drop-outs. These youths are Kantoguans who ought to benefit from the enormous wealth and resources of the nation.<br><br>  Unfortunately, this is not the case at the moment. Indeed, it is the duty of government , especially at the centre, to provide entrepreneurial skill acquisition program and start-up funds for small scale businesses to empower the youths. This will reduce the chances of engagement of youths for wrong purposes.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:413,question:"The responsibility of empowering the youth rests mostly with",option:{a:"the political class",b:"religious organizations",c:"university administrators",d:"national government"},section:"One major trend in Kantoga Republic today, especially during elections, is the engagement of youths by some politicians for political thuggery, rigging, stuffing of ballot boxes and other related electoral offences. Most of the youths who are engaged in these crimes have no means of livelihood or are school drop-outs. These youths are Kantoguans who ought to benefit from the enormous wealth and resources of the nation.<br><br>  Unfortunately, this is not the case at the moment. Indeed, it is the duty of government , especially at the centre, to provide entrepreneurial skill acquisition program and start-up funds for small scale businesses to empower the youths. This will reduce the chances of engagement of youths for wrong purposes.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:414,question:"Based on the write-up, what immediate measures can those in authority take to empower the youths?",option:{a:"Build more youth orientation camps in the country",b:"Enhance religious and moral education in schools and colleges",c:"Provide entrepreneurial training with adequate fund",d:"Provide free meal for the teeming unemployed youths"},section:"One major trend in Kantoga Republic today, especially during elections, is the engagement of youths by some politicians for political thuggery, rigging, stuffing of ballot boxes and other related electoral offences. Most of the youths who are engaged in these crimes have no means of livelihood or are school drop-outs. These youths are Kantoguans who ought to benefit from the enormous wealth and resources of the nation.<br><br>  Unfortunately, this is not the case at the moment. Indeed, it is the duty of government , especially at the centre, to provide entrepreneurial skill acquisition program and start-up funds for small scale businesses to empower the youths. This will reduce the chances of engagement of youths for wrong purposes.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:415,question:"A very important segment of the society which is distinct from government, business and home is the",option:{a:"civil society",b:"public service",c:"mass media",d:"traditional institution"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:416,question:"HIV/AIDS is generally described as terminal in nature because it is",option:{a:"preventable",b:"transmittable",c:"avertable",d:"incurable"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:417,question:"Inter-communal relationship is best described as",option:{a:"the interaction between individuals, groups or organizations with common aspirations",b:"the interaction among individuals and professionals in a social setting",c:"loyalty to community leaders so as to achieve rapid communal development",d:"respect for collective national symbols in order to foster nationalistic feeling"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:418,question:"A situation whereby someone is obliged to inform a superior about his actions and decisions for the purpose of control is",option:{a:"probity",b:"self-discipline",c:"accountability",d:"fair play"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:419,question:"The above quotation summarizes the",option:{a:"Universal Declaration of Human Rights.",b:"African Charter on Human Rights.",c:"Geneva Conventions and Protocols.",d:"United Nations Organization Charter."},section:"“All human beings are born free and equal in dignity and rights. They are endowed with reason and 		conscience and should act towards one another in a spirit of brotherhood”.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:420,question:"Effective and responsible parenthood is primarily",option:{a:"a national duty",b:"a military duty",c:"a political duty",d:"an economic duty"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:421,question:"Association and affiliation between two or more people is called",option:{a:"multilateral relations",b:"bilateral relations",c:"inter-communal relations",d:"interpersonal relations"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:422,question:"A bill passed by the National Assembly requires the assent of the president before it becomes law. The law can be declared null and void by the court of law. The process above emphasizes the",option:{a:"supremacy of judiciary over other arms of government",b:"relationship among the arms of government",c:"importance of law makers in a democracy",d:"fundamentals of the rule of law."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:423,question:"The idea that “Law should be impartial with the people who break it” implies",option:{a:"principle of fair hearing",b:"right to legal representation",c:"equality before the law",d:"prerogative writ of habeas corpus"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:424,question:"The foreign policy objective of Nigeria as enshrined in the 1999 Constitution exclude the promotion of",option:{a:"national interest",b:"African integration",c:"support for donor agencies",d:"just world economic order"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:425,question:"Democracy can promote national development if there is",option:{a:"good governance",b:"promotion of culture",c:"immunity for leaders",d:"registration of parties"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:426,question:"A major civil society group which campaigned against military rule prior to the advent of the Fourth Republic in Nigeria is the",option:{a:"Campaign for Democracy",b:"Save Nigeria Group",c:"Civil Liberties Organization",d:"National Democratic Coalition"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:427,question:"Which of the following function is not performed by the Public Service Commission?",option:{a:"Evaluating the performance of ministries and departments",b:"Advising government on technical matters",c:"Preparing the annual budget and assenting to it",d:"Organizing enlightenment program and training"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:428,question:"Which of the following is a major challenge to civil society in Nigeria?",option:{a:"Value disorientation",b:"Diverse political interests",c:"Inadequate funding",d:"Unstable political system"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:429,question:"Democracy is yet to take firm root in Africa because",option:{a:"it retards African development",b:"African leaders are not experienced enough",c:"most African leaders detest the will of the people",d:"it is an expensive system of government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:430,question:"Nationalism ensures the following except",option:{a:"national consciousness",b:"secession in a country",c:"national integration",d:"unity in a country"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:431,question:"Justice demands that people should always do what is",option:{a:"persistently convenient",b:"consistently right",c:"individually acceptable",d:"courageously necessary"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:432,question:"Orderliness in the society is good mainly because it",option:{a:"discourages poverty",b:"promotes peace and stability",c:"guarantees employment for youths",d:"ensures maximum rewards from leaders"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:433,question:"Which of the following is necessary for the effective application of the rule of law?",option:{a:"Political will to ensure that laws are obeyed",b:"Employment opportunities for all citizens",c:"The fusion of the three arms of government",d:"Extension of the retirement age of judges"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:434,question:"Ade’s action as shown in the dialogue is a demonstration of political",option:{a:"wisdom",b:"apathy",c:"lawlessness",d:"participation"},section:"<strong>Zubar: </strong> Today is the day for gubernatorial elections, Ade what are you waiting for? Let us go and cast our votes for candidates of our choice<br><br> 	<strong>Ade: </strong> I have no interest in an election which not yield any dividend of democracy. Our political elite are only concerned about their interest when they get to the position 	of authority. For crying out loud, I have made up my mind that l will not vote again. <br><br> 	<strong>Zubar: </strong> Haba! Ade, don’t you remember Abraham Lincoln’s words that ‘all men are not just, all men are not true. But ...... for every scoundrel there is a hero, that for every selfish politician, there is a dedicated leader!’ Come on, go and cast your vote so that we can choose the right person for the position and change the political, economic and social directions of our great state.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:435,question:"It could be inferred from the dialogue that failure to vote in an election would",option:{a:"guarantee citizens’ rights",b:"encourage the emergence of responsive government",c:"promote accountability in governance",d:"perpetuate irresponsible leadership"},section:"<strong>Zubar: </strong> Today is the day for gubernatorial elections, Ade what are you waiting for? Let us go and cast our votes for candidates of our choice<br><br> 	<strong>Ade: </strong> I have no interest in an election which not yield any dividend of democracy. Our political elite are only concerned about their interest when they get to the position 	of authority. For crying out loud, I have made up my mind that l will not vote again. <br><br> 	<strong>Zubar: </strong> Haba! Ade, don’t you remember Abraham Lincoln’s words that ‘all men are not just, all men are not true. But ...... for every scoundrel there is a hero, that for every selfish politician, there is a dedicated leader!’ Come on, go and cast your vote so that we can choose the right person for the position and change the political, economic and social directions of our great state.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:436,question:"From the above dialogue, political leaders can encourage citizens to perform their civic duties by",option:{a:"fulfilling their electoral promises",b:"travelling overseas to seek for foreign investors",c:"engaging in religious activities",d:"visiting all the local governments in the country"},section:"<strong>Zubar: </strong> Today is the day for gubernatorial elections, Ade what are you waiting for? Let us go and cast our votes for candidates of our choice<br><br> 	<strong>Ade: </strong> I have no interest in an election which not yield any dividend of democracy. Our political elite are only concerned about their interest when they get to the position 	of authority. For crying out loud, I have made up my mind that l will not vote again. <br><br> 	<strong>Zubar: </strong> Haba! Ade, don’t you remember Abraham Lincoln’s words that ‘all men are not just, all men are not true. But ...... for every scoundrel there is a hero, that for every selfish politician, there is a dedicated leader!’ Come on, go and cast your vote so that we can choose the right person for the position and change the political, economic and social directions of our great state.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"}],i={subject:e,status:200,total:48,data:o};export{o as data,i as default,t as status,e as subject,a as total};
